[music]
Heat. Hey. Hey. Hey.
>> [music]
>> Heat. Heat.
[music]
Heat. Heat.
Hello, good
evening and good day everybody and
welcome back to the Ask Show. This is
episode 300,
the history, the mysteries of history.
Okay. Uh and I'm going to take questions
that you all have asked in the comments.
I've selected a bunch of those
questions. I will take as many of those
questions as possible over the next
couple of hours. So no super chat today
just uh questions from the comments but
let us see who all is there on the live
stream. So who do we have? Mary Kane
good to see you ma'am. Real Vadimir
Putin demon crawler geopolitical dubet
from indor good evening sir. MK hello
Saksham Jotia Vinit Kapper uh Arya 314
good evening demon crawler once again
Ashwini Sharma Shub Shy Gi Pratarana
Namaste Mea Kotari hello General Subutai
hello
Shanks Dhwana Shanks a do I have an ear
for David Bowie well never been
really close to David Bow's music but
I'm sure a couple of his songs I've
heard Yes. All right. Nikita Anesthesia.
Okay. Good to see you the summit. Thanks
so much. Thank you so much. Uh Alan J
Victor Namashkaram from Oman. Good to
have you sir. Namaskarum. Uh Yash
Yashnag Yash Nagar. Hello. Uh who else
do we have? Karthik Prattab Singh. Hello
Swami once again. Demon Crawler Davik
Shrian. Namaste. Anandam S2825. Hello.
MK Shv General Subutai Aayush Singh
Panam Anand Pay Push K Namaskar Sujal
Vinit Kapper Swami is here from Jaipur.
Good to have you sir from Jaipur.
Krishna of the Suries Netherlands always
good to see you. Uh Jay Bonjour from
Martinik France. Bonjour to you sir.
Barat M Kulkarni
uh from New York.
[laughter] Okay. AJ Ajay Ajay Rana.
Crazy brain. Good evening. Good to see
you. Crazy brain. Good to see you. Uh
Gopol says Niha Shangji sir. I think I'm
acquiring a new Chinese name or
something. Yes. Uh I I'm on the lookout
for a Chinese name. We have a new
ambassador to China who's been
appointed. The new Indian ambassador to
China. He has a a Chinese name in
addition to his own Indian name. So it
looks like you can acquire an an
additional name. So I am on the lookout
for a Chinese name for myself in case
some of you have some uh
recommendations. I'll take those. Da
Lanya from Jaipur. Good evening.
Namaste. Uh Amrit Singh Har Mahadev.
Arismanticor. Swami says, "Have you
watched young Frankenstein?" I may have
watched it. Is it a black and white
movie?
Is it a funny movie? I may have seen it.
[laughter]
AB normal. Is that the one? I can think
of some other things too. Yeah. Okay. I
think I've seen that. The guy with the
eyes. Yes. Okay. Nirvana Shanks once
again. Da Lanya Sam the gamer. Good.
Good morning. Real Madrir Ramji Omnayak
and everyone else. Okay. I will be able
I will I will stop now otherwise I'll be
greeting you all day and all all night.
Adil Ben good evening and everyone else.
Okay. Okay. Let us uh uh Jatin Shukla
has just came back from Jaipur
dialogues. All right. Uh Vi very easier
from NJ New Jersey. Well, good to have
you sir. Good morning. Okay, let's get
going with some questions. What
questions do we have today? Um various
questions. Yes, let's take the
questions. What's the first question is
by Rushab T. Who are the Drews people
and what's their belief system? What
similarities does the Drew's faith have
with the Abrahamic religions? Why is it
considered mysterious and secret where
no one can convert or intermar?
Is it true that the Drews religion has
many similarities or some simil
similarities with Zoroastrianism and
Hinduism? Can the Drews be put in the
same basket as Jazidis and Kurs or are
they different? The Drews people. Who
are these Drews people? So, there are a
small uh religious group, Arabic
speaking religious group that is found
in West Asia in Jordan, Syria, parts of
Israel,
Lebanon as well. And the total number is
approximately 1 million people. Okay. So
if you look at the map it's in uh the
these people they live in West Asia kind
of you know similar region as the uh
Kurs and the Yazidis.
So the Yazidis are found in northern
Iraq. Um and the U Drews people are
found in Syria, Lebanon, uh Jordan,
Israel, maybe maybe Iraq. I'm not sure
about Iraq, but definitely western Asia,
the eastern Mediterranean seabboard,
that region. Okay. Small population
about a million people. There are some
Jews people in Venezuela as well,
apparently in South America. Maybe a few
a few tens of thousands, that sort of
thing. So that that's where these people
live, the Drews people. Okay. Uh they
are an Arabic speaking people and their
religion is a monotheistic religion and
they say that the god they worship is
the god that the Jews, Muslims and
Christians worship, same god. So that
means that this is an Abrahamic
religion. A minor
Abrahamic religion, one of the Abrahamic
religions but a small number of people
practice this religion.
Uh let's let's uh find out how many
people practice Judaism globally. Let's
find out. Uh how many million will that
be? Let me see how many Jews in Okay. In
the world, how many
uh what's the total Jewish population?
Okay. 14 million. 15 14 15 million.
That's that's the that's the global
Jewish population. So the Drews are
about 115th of that.
Okay. So, pretty small population. So,
now what are the characteristics of the
religion? First of all, it like I said,
it's a monotheistic religion. It's an
Abrahamic religion. Their God is the
same God as that of that of the Jews and
Christians and Muslims.
uh they believe in the the prophets that
the Abrahamic people believe in uh Moses
and uh Noah and Jesus and Muhammad and
whoever else the the the Abrahamic
prophets are Abraham obviously right uh
and so on
what else is there in the religion what
what what what makes it unique so what
makes their religion unique
is that they don't believe in a day of
judgment
They don't believe in heaven or and
hell.
The Jews people they believe in
reincarnation.
What? Abrahamic religion, monotheistic
religion, but they believe in
reincarnation. Well, yes, they believe
in reincarnation.
Um, so that's that's what makes the
religion unique. And they have their own
um uh holy texts or something. I don't
know what they called. Okay, you can
look it up. uh I cannot remember foreign
terminology uh Arabic terminology. So
they have some some uh holy texts of
their own minimal holy texts not like
extensive documentation or literature
uh and they don't uh intermar they they
practice monogamy not polygamy that's
another difference between their
religion and the u and for example Islam
so they they don't marry multiple wives
um they don't uh convert out of the
religion, you can't convert into their
religion. That's not allowed. So let's
say you are somebody who practices some
other religion and you say, "Yeah, you
know what? I want to convert to
Drewism." Whatever. It's not allowed.
You can't do that. So you can be Drews
only if your parents were Drews
that sort of thing. So it's a pretty
insular kind of uh religion. Um it is
said to have similarities with
Zoroastrianism and Hinduism. The
clearest similarity is that they believe
in reincarnation.
That is what the dharmic u
religions or faiths or culture believes
in, right? Reincarnation.
So the the Jews believe in that. Uh but
they believe that if if you are a male
person, the moment you die, you are
reincarnated immediately in a different
body. And if you are male, then you will
be reincarnated male only. And if you're
a female, you will only be reincarnated
as a female. So there's no
cross-pollination of genders or
whatever. In the dharmic uh system, you
can be a male in one birth and a female
in another lifetime, right? But in the
Drews system, if you're male, you're
male forever, no matter how many times
you're reborn, that sort of thing. Um so
that's about the Drews people. Um they
have been persecuted historically at
various points in time. uh in more
recent day, recent years, they have been
uh uh the target of massacres by ISIS,
right? So the Drews have been treated by
ISIS the same way that they treated the
Yazidis.
Not sure about the Kurs. So can the
Drews be put in the same basket as the
Yazidis and Kuds? Well, the Yazidis
aren't an Abrahamic. Uh their their
religion isn't Abrahamic. I'm not sure
if they are considered to be Abrahamic.
The Yazidis
they do say that their religion is
monotheistic Yazidi religion but clearly
it has way more elements of Indian
culture than the Drews religion. So the
Yazidi religion is different and the
Yazidi people also aren't Arabic. They
may perhaps speak Arabic today because
of circumstances but they are not an
Arabic people. They are an Indo-Iranian
people. The the Yazidis even the Kurds
are Indo-Iranian.
They speak a Persian or Iranian religion
and the Kur they practice Islam standard
Sunni Islam if I'm not mistaken and the
Drews faith religion it's it's a
descendant of a Shiite form of Islam
right a pretty interesting and unique
religion small Abrahamic religion
descended from Shiite Islam Shia Islam
um and they believe in reincarnation and
they have some peculiarities that are
absent in mainstream Islam or the other
Abrahamic religions. So that's the Drews
people. Pretty interesting um religion
that they have.
Um okay, I suppose that's the answer.
All right, next.
Rushabar once again says, "How did
Russia retain the permanent seat in the
United Nations Security Council after
the USSR disintegrated?
Didn't the US try to block Russia?
[clears throat] They had an excellent
opportunity in 1991 to remove Russia
permanently and isolate it. So why did
the US not grab it? Replacing communist
China or Taiwan is a prime example of
replacement. The Russians had a weak
leader Boris Yelson. So why did the US
step back?
So here's what happened in the early
'90s 199192. That's that's around the
time when the USSR disintegrated.
Okay. Gorbachev steps down. Yelson takes
over. There is chaos in Moscow. Uh the
White House of Moscow, the parliament
building is is is bombarded. There's
lawmakers stuck inside. Yelen on the
streets. He climbs on top of a tank and
shouts democracy, democracy, or whatever
he shouts. Yeah, it was pretty young and
much more sober at the time. And there's
chaos across the length and the breadth
of the USSR. And more than 10 republics,
SSRs secede from the union from the
union of Soviet Socialist Republics. So
these are the uh Commonwealth of
independent states, the Stans and so on
so forth. The Baltic states, Lithuania,
Latvia, Estonia and the Stans,
Usbakistan, Tajakistan, Kajakistan,
Kyrgystan, so on so forth so forth. So
all these little little and large states
seceded from the USSR and what was left?
What was left was what is today Russia.
Okay. So now the question for the United
States was how do we deal with this
potentially super chaotic situation? Why
potentially super chaotic? because the
USSR was a superpower and their assets
were distributed among these various
newly emerged nations in addition to a
lot of most of the assets being in
Russia. Now the assets that concerned
the US were nuclear weapons. You had
Soviet nuclear weapons in various
various parts of the USSR and now many
of these parts of the USSR were now
independent.
And even for these newly independent
republics, those nuclear weapons were
like hot potatoes. They did not want to
have those. So they all get together,
okay? The former Soviet republics, they
all get together and they decide, you
know what? Let's give all of this back
to Russia and we will tell the world
that Russia should should continue on in
the U in the United Nations in place of
the earthws and we are completely fine
with that. So all the earthw wild Soviet
republics, newly independent Soviet
republics, they came together and they
announced that we want Russia
to be the continuation of the USSR
in the context of the United Nations and
the United Nations Security Council. So
that was the will of the uh newly
independent Soviet republics. Now you
have the US. The US has just won a major
victory, a victory that was decades in
the making. They have defeated the USSR.
They have disintegrated the USSR.
And the US was now worried that what if
there is proliferation of nuclear
weapons. Usbakistan says I want to have
78 nukes. Tajakistan says I want to have
15. And what if there's chaos and and
these all nations you know that power
goes to their head and they start acting
crazy. So the US also wanted a stable
situation.
So they supported the commonwealth of
independent states and the transfer of
the nuclear weapons whichever where
wherever to the to the Russians. They
the Americans even ensure that Ukraine
transfer transfers its nukes to Russia
and the US was perfectly okay with
Russia continuing as the successor state
of the USSR in the United Nations and
the United Nations Security Council.
Why? Why this? We understand we can we
can understand that the US did not want
proliferation of nuclear warheads. But
why allow Russia to continue on in the
UN security council? In the UN security
council, you have special privileges.
You see the post 1945 world order was a
hierarchical order and there was a
privileged bunch of nations. Five the P5
nations. the five nations that are
permanent members of the UN security
council which is the US, Russ, USSR,
China, uh the UK and force.
Now USSR was to be replaced with Russia.
Why did the US allow this to happen?
Because the US at the time believed that
they were in complete control of the
universe. They were now the lords and
masters of the universe. Russia was this
broken country with a devastated economy
and a leader that was a US asset
apparently Boris Yelson even Gorbachev
most likely was a US asset in some way
or the other right the US thought that
we have them
by by whatever hurts the most [laughter]
so then let them continue and we got to
control them completely so you have
after the disintegration of the USSR you
have Gorbachov appearing in a Pizza Hut
commercial. So that's the kind of
infiltration the Americans had achieved
in the in the earthw wild USSR by that
point in time that Gorbachov the former
president of the USSR
one of the two most powerful men on
earth now appeared in a Pizza Hut
commercial and you had the friendly with
Clinton and so on. So the Americans
thought we are in full control. Let them
continue on in the UN security council.
And if they did not allow Russia to
continue in the UN security council that
would create some kind of uh crisis in
the UN security council because the
original charter would no longer apply
and all kinds of procedural issues and
so on. So just to smooth things over the
Americans said okay let it continue let
the Russians continue as was one of the
P5 nations and we we'll be able to deal
with them. And as long as Yelson was
there, Russia was was under American
control. I mean, Russia was under
control. Not directly under US control
obviously, but under control. Things
were under control. It's only when
there's a transition from Jelson to
Putin that then after a few years, the
Americans started wondering what what on
earth has happened here. Something has
gone wrong. Putin isn't what we
expected. But by that time, it was too
late. Right? By the time it was too late
to change things. So the Americans did
not want to permanently isolate Russia.
They wanted to infiltrate Russia. They
wanted to take over Russia's resources.
Um they wanted to destroy the Russian
economy further. And for some time they
kind of achieved that, right? Russia
wasn't in chaos. There were the two
church wars. First Chuchchin war was a
disaster for Russia. Yelsen lost it for
Russia.
Um
and yeah, so the Americans didn't want
to isolate Russia. They want to remove
Russia permanently. They wanted Russia
to be a new US vasal,
you know, the nation with the largest
resources in the world. Why why
isolated? Bring it integrated into it
into the American western economy,
right? That's what the Americans wanted.
So in in hindsight, maybe it was not a
very wise move, but at the at that time,
it was the uniolar moment. It was a
moment of euphoria. It was a moment of
invincibility. I mean, apparent
invincibility for the US. They were the
now the
the rulers of the universe, the masters
of the universe. And that's why they
were perfectly happy for this to happen.
But today, well, after the Ukraine war
started, the Ukrainians have been
raising questions about whether the u
whether allowing Russia to continue on
as the successor state of the USSR as a
P5 nation. Was that legal? Was that
right? The Ukrainians have been raising
questions about that, but that's like 35
years too late, right? So, okay, what's
done is done. It's a done deal. It's a
feta comp like they would say in French.
Okay, next question.
And the next question is by
by
it's by Rushab Tar once again. Okay,
Rushab Tar is on a roll today. The
question is if China invented gunpowder,
why did it remain so backward compared
to the modern artillery of the
Europeans? Did the Chinese emperors make
the same mistakes which Indian emperors
made or were there other reasons why
they did not really use gunpowder for
military purposes or did they not think
that this will be used against them in a
different way okay so the question of
gunpowder it's a pretty vexed question
it's a pretty controversial question
because there is significant evidence
that actually it's India that invented
gunpowder but the European scholars and
Indian historians and so on they
attributed they gave the credit to China
first that the Chinese invented. So we
will not get into the debate for the
context and purpose of this question.
Okay, most likely it was India that
invented gunpowder but the credit isn't
given. You ask chat GPT I suppose it
will say no no China. You ask Google it
will say no no China did it. Shall we do
that? Let's do that before we uh Okay,
let's do that before we actually address
this question. Okay. Which civilization
invented gunpowder?
There we have it. See, so that's the
they'll say China. So we will not go
into that controversial question right
now. But assuming
that China was using gunpowder thousand
years ago, which it was in that context,
let's consider this. So China the see
China was using there were periods of
time after the Tang dynasty where there
was conflict in China. after each
imperial cycle there's a period of chaos
in China and you sometimes have two or
three dynasties that are competing for
hgemony and so on so forth uh the song
versus the whoever and so on so there
were so about 1100 or so years ago we
know that the Chinese were using
gunpowder against each other okay they
were using gunpowder
um and Chinese uh emperors had salt
peter they used to have they used to
have the standardized production of salt
peter and sulfur and so on which are
components of of gunpowder and gunpowder
weapons were used in pretty standardized
ways. Uh the Chinese had these uh spears
in which at the front you would have
gunpowder and that would explode and it
would emit shrapnel which essentially is
the one of the oldest depictions of a
firearm of a handheld firearm like you
know like today you have rifles and so
on that sort of thing that's a precursor
precursor of handheld firearms and there
were rockets that the Chinese used and
uh you know bombs of various kinds and
handheld weapons and projectiles and
rockets means missiles and so on. The
Chinese did use this in warfare. It's
not like the Chinese did not use it in
warfare but they use it against each
other. Okay. And eventually once Chinese
empires stabilized during an imperial
cycle there would be no other challenger
within China. And then the challengers
would be those on the outskirts of
China, those who lived in the steps, the
Tatars,
the Turk tribes, the Mongols and so on.
Right?
And generally, and these were nomadic
peoples. These were nomadic peoples. And
gunpowder wasn't relevant to defeating
them.
See, gunpowder in the ancient days, it
was used in siege warfare. It was used
in pitched battles where you have a
battlefield on which you have two two
armies that have come face to face and
they said okay they decided okay today
we're going to fight we're going to see
who wins in that
situation which is called a pitched
battle gunpowder and and firearms and
rockets and bombs and projectiles are
relevant
or if you have siege warfare where you
have one uh where you have an army that
has besieged a castle or a city and
you're using projectiles and gunpowder,
you know, projectiles and bombs and
whatnot to try and break down the walls.
In that situation, once again, gunpowder
is relevant. But when you have a
situation where you have horse riding uh
archers who are coming at you on all
directions, uh those
older variations of gunpowder weapons
were not were not relevant. So when it
comes to the Chinese emperor empires
fighting off uh the nomadic step tribes
like the Tatars, the Turic tribes, the
Mongols and etc. Gunpowder wasn't
relevant.
So because of that gunpowder usage
continued but it never uh it was never
iteratively improved in a in a rapid uh
manner. Okay. So gunpowder was used uh
in China during the Yuan dynasty and
after the Yuan dynasty. Yuan the Yuan
dynasty was a conquest dynasty. It was
founded by Shri Chingghis Khan right? So
it was a Mongol dynasty that ruled China
for a while. Kubla Khan was their first
great emperor of course but
retrospectively it's Chingish Khan who
was the first who was the founder and so
on. After the Yuan dynasty, you have
theQing dynasty, right?
And once the once these dynasties take
over the whole of China, they don't
really they do not really feel the need
to iteratively and rapidly improve their
weapons and artillery and all that
improve by by using it. And overall, you
know, you use it, you find some defect
in deficiency, you find some some scope
for improvement and you make that
improvement. Then again, you use it,
then over time, you keep improving
improving and that's how your weapons
get better. That situation never arose
in China. Now let's consider Europe. At
some point in time then powder reaches
Europe. And in Europe you had a totally
different situation. Europe was this
mass of small states, nation states,
kingdoms,
duchies,
principalities
and so on who are constantly fighting
each other. The European tribal wars.
The the region of Europe is a very
tribalistic region.
all kinds of petty conflicts they always
fighting each other. So in the middle
ages etc there was constant warfare in
Europe
constant warfare petty warfare larger
scale warfare but constant warfare and
because of that there was a tremendous
incentive in Europe for weapons to be
iteratively rapidly improved because
whoever made even a small improvement
had a qualitative and qualitative
advantage over their adversaries. And
when that happened, adversaries were
also incentivized to very rapidly
address the the the gap in capabilities.
And that's why you had very rapid
iterative improvement of artillery and
so on and gunpowder weapons in Europe
and eventually these were standardized
and European engineers and scientists
were also incentivized to uh get
involved in this which obviously once
you have engineers and scientists
getting involved in this uh things
improve rapidly. So on the one one hand
in Europe you have constant improvement
over years over decades over centuries.
In China you had stagnation because
there was no need to there was no urgent
pressing need to keep improving the
weapons. So eventually by the 16 17
1800s there was a situation where the
Chinese had to start importing superior
European weapons
right and eventually obviously because
by the time they had fallen behind in
their capabilities and technology so the
it's like the Chinese uh thousand years
before today they were using gunpowder
the Europeans had no idea what gunpowder
was but by the 1800s the Europeans were
far ahead of the Chinese so it's it it's
a process that took 800 900 years right
it did not happen over a couple of weeks
So it's it's a process that took took
time and over time everything changes
right I mean India invented mathematics
but look at where India is today
compared to the west right where does
all the research and u all that happen
today where do all the advancements
happen they happen in the west India
came up with all of these concepts that
are the backbone of modern mathematics
and science but today India is nowhere
right so things change over time but
that process takes centuries.
Okay.
So you can't really blame the Chinese
for this. Their their situation was
different. Their their uh the challenges
they faced were different. They were
very very different from the challenges
the Europeans faced. That's why the
Europeans because of the ch those
challenges improve very rapidly.
Rishabad Gowami says please don't get
angry. Mhm. Don't get angry. [laughter]
I have a sensitive question. Okay.
What's your sensitive question? If our
ancient Gurugul and temple university
systems were so intellectually superior,
why did they fail to produce the
industrial and military scale needed to
stop the colonial factory system? Was
the failure in our minds or just our
inability to scale the brilliance to the
masses?
So we just now discussed
why China who is said to have invented
gunpowder why did China the supposed
inventor of gunpowder eventually fall
behind the Europeans in firearms and
artillery significantly behind.
Similarly,
India is the nation that essentially
it's it's the civilization that invented
higher education, systematic education,
philosophy, science, the scientific
method, mathematics, all of that through
the gurugal system, through the temple
university system, through the vishwa
vidylaya system and so on. India is the
pioneer and inventor of standardized
education. Right? India gave this to the
world
and yet look at where today where India
is today. India has one of the worst
education systems in the world. You can
keep harping on NEP 2020 or whatever the
hell you want to harp on if you're the
government of India, but it's trash.
It's garbage. right now. Go back a
couple of centuries, three centuries,
and you had the the the Europeans who by
the 1600s were intruding, introgressing
into India, and they had their colonial
colonial they were establishing, setting
up the the the the um um you know the
seeds of the colonial factory system and
so on, right?
So why did our gurugul and temple
education system which was so allegedly
intellectually superior why did it fail
to keep up with the Europeans? That's
the question Rishab is asking and Rishab
is worried that I'll get angry. No, it's
a good question. Well the answer is
by the 1600s 1700s the temple education
system and university education system
was extinct.
Especially the university education
system it was completely extinct.
India's universities which were very
numerous in quantity many of them we
don't even know what they were called
anymore they are in ruins but we know a
few the Chashila Nananda Odantaapuri
Tilhara
Shardit
and so many more right so many more um
Walabi and yeah we had so many of these
universities all over the place these
were all destroyed a thousand years ago
and then India gradually came under Turk
occupation and the Turks sought to
eradicate
at the roots India's culture. So they
destroyed temples all across northern
and western India, Eastern India as
well. Southern India temples survived to
some extent but northern India was
ravaged. West India was ravaged. Even
Eastern India was eventually ravaged.
So if your universities are burned to
the to ashes, the libraries are burned
to ashes.
the they are dismantled brick by brick.
If your temples are destroyed, if your
gurus, your teachers are beheaded,
um how do you expect that system to
still produce industrial and military
scale needed to stop something that
happens in the 1600s, 1700s, 1800s? How
do you expect that?
You understand chronologically the
problem? The universities were destroyed
around 1,00 or 1100 AD.
The temples by 1500 AD in northern west
and eastern India were mostly destroyed.
India was under foreign occupation.
India was under siege. India's culture,
civilization and people were under
siege.
The Indian system no longer by the time
functioned the way it was supposed to
function. It was barely surviving. The
whole civilization, the whole population
was in survival mode.
We were way down here in Masslo's
hierarchy of needs. When you're way down
here, survival mode in Masslo's
hierarchy of needs, how can you achieve
the higher order,
you know, aspirations of of of human
society? You can't. Do you understand?
So that is what happened.
So the Turks ravaged India, destroyed
India. And when the Turks Turk empire
started declining eventually that's when
the Europeans this they they stepped in
to fill the vacuum of power in various
parts of India. Eventually the Marata
Empire did rise and reclaim and and and
and liberate India for a while from Turk
occupation but then
they too failed
and that's when the English took over.
So that is what happened. Please
understand that there was no temple
education system, university education
system in 16,700, 1800.
At some level lower
education still continued until the n
until the 1800s.
So lower education in village temples
etc continued until until the 1800s
but not higher education. So lower
education means teaching arithmetic and
grammar and that sort of thing. 2 + 2=
4, 10 * 12 is equal to 120, 17 * 3 is
whatever and so on. That sort of basic
education was there.
So that's what happened. You see
Rushabare once again says what was the
Spanish Armada and why was it sent? Why
did the Spanish Armada fail and how
Queen Elizabeth built the British fleet,
the seeds of British naval power? How
did it shape the eventual British
colonization of the Americas in Asia and
India? Could it be considered an
inflection point in history as it gave
rise to the Royal Navy, a navy that
ruled across oceans?
Okay. So, um the Spanish Armada,
the Spanish Armada, um
the Spanish Armada was from what
[snorts] 1588 was it?
Was it 1588? I think it was 1588 when
you have um Elizabeth.
Okay. So, let's understand the context.
H [clears throat]
we are talking about 1588 late 16th
century.
Queen Elizabeth has been in has been in
power for some time. Britain is once
again a Protestant nation. Now let's
understand the context.
Queen Elizabeth's father was King Henry
VII.
This is a fantastic guy. Okay,
brilliant, very interesting guy. You can
make a movie series, TV series about
him. I'm sure there are.
So the guy married six, seven, I don't
know, five, six wives, beheaded half of
them. Uh his first wife was Katherine of
Aragon, Spanish.
Um
and her she produced one daughter that
is married married to her. Then uh King
Henry VII wanted a male child. So he had
a male child with with one of his
mistresses. But the male child died
pretty young. I suppose he was king for
a bit. Then he married Anne Bolain with
Anne Bolain once again. He had a female
child that's Elizabeth. Then he had an
Molain dispatched and he married I think
at least three more ladies.
I forget the Katherine Par and
whoever the names are not An of Cleaves.
Yeah, there was a marriage with Anof
Cleaves as well. German lady but it was
Anel and so on so forth. Long story. So
after Henry VIII died, see Henry VIII,
okay, he was born Catholic. England was
Catholic at the time, but he wanted to
divorce his first wife uh Katherine of
Aragon, but for that he needed the per
the permission from the pope. A king
needed the pope's permission to divorce
uh his wife and the pope refused to give
permission. So the king said, Henry the
said that you know what, I renounce the
Catholic Church. I'm going to set up my
own church of England, the Anglican
church. England is now going to be
Protestant henceforth.
And so he divorced uh Katherine of
Aragon, married Anne Bolain um and had
Elizabeth with with her. So after he
dies for a while, his son is king I
think if I'm not mistaken, but he dies
young and then Mary the daughter of
Katherine of Aragon becomes queen of
England. Now Mary, Mary says Mary was
the daughter of a Catholic queen and her
father was also Catholic when Mary was
born and her father divorced her mother
and became Protestant to marry Anbolain.
So Mary once she became queen she she
undid whatever her father did and and
made England Catholic again and then she
went after you know she executed a reign
of terror in England and and went after
all the Protestants and that's why she
was called a bloody Mary maybe some of
it is propaganda or whatever but she's
remembered as a very cruel king queen
and she's remembered as bloody Mary but
eventually Mary dies and Elizabeth
becomes queen and she once again turns
England in Protestant. So during Henry
VII's time it's it's Catholicism then
Protestantinism
then Mary comes to power Catholicism
again then Elizabeth comes to power
protestantism again now the Spanish were
Protestants uh sorry they were Catholics
and they hated the Protestants
so now let's understand the geopolitical
situation
by the 15 mid 1500s the Spanish were in
possession of vast terri terries in the
Americas. See 1492 Christopher Columbus
announced that I have discovered India
but turned out to be a new continent.
Okay, the Americas
and uh by the 15 mid 1500s the the
Spanish had taken over Cuba uh present
day Dominican Republica,
Central America, parts of South America,
Venezuela and so on. They already had
this big big big
empire,
imperial possessions in the Americas and
they had the they had the encoma system
of slavery and genocide and all that and
they were extracting tremendous amounts
of wealth out of the Americas and they
had a powerful naval fleet the
Spaniards.
Now the English they had this modest
naval naval fleet and they could not
compete with the Spanish in outright
warfare. So the English under Elizabeth
they took a different approach. It was
called privateeering. Private hearering
or private hearering? Private hearering.
Privateier. The spelling is P R I V A T
E R. Okay. P R I V A T E R.
Privateier. A person a private person or
ship that engages in maritime warfare
under a commission of war. Now if you
rearrange the words private here, what
do you get? Let's remove the R pi.
Okay, let's let's take the uh R and put
it after I p I R remove the V A T E.
Pirate private here means pirate
actually. Okay. So Elizabeth
under uh her rule you had English
pirates who were raiding Spanish ships
and stealing their treasure and slaves
and whatnot. Okay, officially the
government of England was not involved
in this but unofficially Elizabeth was
behind all of that. So this was piracy.
So in England is the nation that gave
the world piracy
and all the cruelty that was assoc ass
associated with that and it gave rise to
the pirates of the Caribbean movies I
suppose eventually.
So this was obviously theft and plunder
and contravention of international law
and whatnot of that time and that's what
Elizabeth was doing.
So these pirate ships were pretty lean
and mean ships, lowbuilt ships with
cannons and they were they they did
plunder and theft and all that. So
eventually the Spaniards got tired of
this and they said let us build the big
Armada, a big naval fleet of 130 ships
and we will take this gigantic naval
fleet of big huge massive heavy
powerfully armed 130 ships. We're going
to invade England. We're going to depose
Elizabeth, do regime change operation.
We're going to install a puppet regime
of our own and we're going to we're
going to change the religion once again
to Catholicism and we will rule England.
Okay? And we will some of the ships that
they had orange trees because the
Spanish wanted orange trees in England
when when they would rule England and so
on. So they were they were certain they
would succeed. So about 130 ships were
launched from Spain. big massive ships
compared to the Spanish gallions and
ships. The English naval ships were
tiny, small, lowbuilt. Uh they could not
even do any, you know, boarding
activities, you know, boarding the other
ship. And they had cannons. The Spanish
had like god knows how many cannons.
English ships would have like four, five
maybe cannons or whatever, whatever the
number was, right? Um so it was it
looked like a mismatch. And the English
ships were smaller in number also. I
don't know how many ships they had but
significantly significantly less than
the number of Spanish ships which is 130
roughly 130. So the Spanish launch the
Armada and Elizabeth comes to know about
this and she orders her navy to go and
defend uh England the kingdom and
there's this naval engagement and what
you find is that the English ships are
very agile very nimble they're fast
moving they can't be boarded they can
fight at standoff distances
of contemporary standoff ranges and they
destroyed to some extent the Spanish
fleet
The Spanish could not match the the the
the agility, the nimleness, the
maneuverability and the firepower of the
English ships. They could not board the
English ships and fight the way they
were they they were accustomed to
fighting. Boarding means you have two
large ships who will come close to each
other and then you will put ladders on
top and you will jump with swords in
your hand and then you'll go clash.
That's boarding. But when you have a big
ship and a small ship and the small ship
is agile and faster, you can't board the
small ship. So that that manner of
warfare is gone.
So it's it's you know it's what it's
reminiscent of kind of you have a very
powerful 21st century army with all
kinds of extremely expensive weapons and
that can be taken out by inexpensive
drones and large quantities of ballistic
missiles kind of like that. So the
English redefined the nature of naval
warfare. They defeated the Spanish
Armada and then the Armada to to pour
insult on injury or salt on the wounds.
It was c it was caught in big u storms
and a lot of these ships were dashed
against rocks and one of them many of
them were sunk. Some of them were ship
shipwrecked off the coast of Scotland,
Ireland, wherever and they were people
the the sailors were killed by the
natives that sort of thing. So it was an
absolute disaster for Spain. So that was
the Spanish Armada which failed
completely. Uh now how did this u was
this an inflection point in history? Did
this give rise to the Royal Navy? No, it
did not give rise to the Royal Navy. The
Royal Navy already existed. Half of the
Royal Navy was a bunch of pirates,
absolute cut-throat barbarians.
Okay. Uh but it it proved to the British
into the world that this is the right
way to do warfare going forward. Okay.
Uh
and uh the Spanish once again built a
fleet, but they never tried. So it was
not the end of the Spanish navy or
whatever. The Spanish had tremendous
resources. They had all this gold and
whatnot flowing in from the Americas. So
they were able to able to rebuild a navy
but they never attempted an invasion of
England again. Okay. The last successful
invasion of England was in the year
1066. After that England has never been
successfully invaded until now when you
have the Pakistanis and all grouping
gangs who have invaded England take a
war. That's a different story.
So that is a different story. But yeah
um
so that is what happened. But it's kind
of an inflection point because it gave
rise to a new new way of doing warfare
and it it was a proof of concept for the
British you know and that's the basis on
which the Royal Navy was built in larger
numbers and the ships that they built
were based on the ships that succeeded
against the Spanish Armada and
eventually the British naval power
became the backbone initial backbone of
the expanding British Empire and this
gave rise to eventually the Royal Navy
but the Royal Navy already kind of
existed at this
Um and yeah it did shape eventually the
British colonization because of the
expanding navy of the trade routes and
eventually the colonization of India and
the Americas and so on. So 1588 is when
this event happened. By 15 1510 or so
the British had put a foothold in the
Americas uh which was Jamestown disaster
absolute disaster. And then you had
Plymouth about a decade or so later
whatever the dates are by by by by what
1720 or something you had Plymouth and
Jamestown and Plymouth both have both
have happened. Rono also happened which
is a totally different story and
eventually the British were the big
winners in the Americas right we know
that uh so that's how it went with the
Spanish Armada.
[clears throat]
Rishabat Tag Gowami says in light of the
direct assassinations of sovereign heads
of state and the bypassing of the UN
security council in the current ongoing
Iran um versus Israel and US conflict.
Has the 1648 Westfallian concept of
state sovereignty finally being replaced
by a civilizational might doctrine where
only four or five pole nations have
actual rights. The rest are merely
buffer zones.
Okay. Okay. So, I would not agree it's a
civilizational might doctrine. It's an
imperial might doctrine because the US
isn't a civilization. It's an empire.
Okay. It's imperial might or military
might doctrine. It's not civilizational
might. Now, coming back to what you're
asking. So, what have we had? This is
kind of a a question that's that's on
the border. That's that's both history
and geopolitics and that's why I've
taken it. So what we've had in this
current ongoing Iran conflict is the
Americans and Israelis have taken out
the they have assassinated
the supreme leader of Iran, the head of
state of Iran, um the Ayatah Ali Kabi,
right? And they've assassinated various
lots of scientists, engineers,
um generals and highranking Iranian
officials.
um you know the number two person Ali
Larij larijani or whoever he was he was
assassinated a few days ago. So this is
a totally this is extremely unusual
essentially unheard of in the
Westfallian system even when you have
two nations at war you don't assassinate
heads of state you don't do that this is
extremely unusual it's unheard of
actually so what's the westfallian
system the westfallian concept of state
sovereignty
um the
world order is the Westfallian or world
order, right? Westfallian sovereignty,
Westfallian world order. So in the
Westfallian system, you have nation
states. Okay? And theoretically or
technically each nation state is
sovereign which means that it has
according to international law complete
control over its territory its
population and it and you know not and
no nation is is allowed to interfere in
the internal affairs of other nations.
So if I'm a sovereign nation, I can have
my own laws, my own rule, my own con
rules, my own constitution, my own norms
of how to govern my nation and my people
and my territory. I can have a
democracy. I can have a theocracy. I can
have a dictatorship. I can have
whatever. It's my internal matter.
Everybody else mind your own godamn
business. That is the concept of
Westfallian sovereignty. Complete
sovereignty over the your territory,
your and your people. That's Westfall
sovereignty. And it doesn't matter how
large or small a nation is, as long as
you are an internationally recognized
nation state, no matter how large or
small you are, you are supposed to be
exempt from uh foreign interference in
your internal affairs.
[clears throat and cough]
So that's the theoretical or technical
concept of Westfallian sovereignty.
Now
uh the post 1945 system, the postc world
war system is not exactly
a system of equal rights for nations.
It's a two-tier system. It's a
hierarchical system. On the one hand,
you have the the privileged nations.
That's the P5 nations. The five
permanent members of the UN Security
Council. These five nations are
privileged nations. Other nations are
non-privileged nations. What privilege
do the P5 nations have? Well, they have
the allimportant veto in the United
Nations Security Council. What does this
veto
what's the role of this veto? So, the
veto allows the P5 nations to block
the enforcement of international law
wherever their interests are concerned.
So if there's something that goes
against the interest of a P5 nation,
that P5 nation can uni un unilaterally
block the execution and implementation
and enforcement of international law.
That is a very powerful weapon to have
the veto. So India was was offered a P5
membership multiple times at least three
times by the US and USSR. But India
under the great Mr. Nehu uh insisted
that this be given to China and that's
why China is a P5 nation today. India is
not. Now that's a different story. So
you have a
you have a hierarchical system since
1945. Okay. The privileged P5 nations
and the rest of the world the riffraff.
Okay. Now since the early 1990s
things were once again redefined. The
early 1990s you had the break up of the
USSR and Russia became a P5 nation the
successor state of the USSR. But Russia
was very weak. Right? And this was the
uniolar moment of the US. So 1990s
onwards you had uh you know reshaping of
of rules. You had uh sovereignty as
responsibility and humanitarian inter
interventions. So what was the concept
of humanitarian intervention? When you
have a sovereign nation that according
to the international community is not
able to fulfill um its governance and
other requirements. It's not able to
take care of its people. Then the
international community by consensus can
intervene in in a for humanitarian
purposes in the nation which means the
so-called international community can
violate the nation's sovereignty for
humanitarian reasons.
Okay. And then you had something called
sovereignty as responsibility which
again is the same thing that you are
sovereign as long as you are acting
responsibility responsibly as per the
norms laid down by the international
community.
But if you are violating the norms laid
down by the international community
whatever they may be then well you we
can violate your sovereignty. So let's
say you are not democratic enough or
let's say uh you know democracy is black
backsliding in your nation apparently or
or or if let's say there is a religious
persecution in n in your nation. In
those circumstances,
you are not fulfilling your your
responsibilities as as a responsible
member of the glo of the world order of
the international committee of nations
and that's why because of that we can
intervene in your nation and interfere
in your internal affairs and these are
big sticks that the west uses to beat
other nations with the west means the
US. So what is this international
community?
The international community let's let's
let's find the definition of the
international community.
Give me a second.
I I'll try and pull that out of Twitter
if it's available. International
community.
Give me a second. I'm sure there's a
good representation of that.
International community.
Let us see. Do we have
international? Okay.
What is this international community?
Right? That's the question we asking
ourselves.
Give me a second. Here we are, sir. So,
the international community that
determines whether humanitarian
intervention should happen or not. This
is the international community. This
this is the international community.
These are the only nations that matter
in the international community. So,
these nations hold the world hostage and
that's the situation. Okay. That's been
the situation since the 1990s.
Okay. So, you have a situation today
where powerful nations
can break international law and you have
a situation where powerful nations are
they are increasingly willing to accept
the political costs
of breaking of of violating
international law
and violating the sovereignty of of uh
technically sovereign nations.
as long as their interests are
safeguarded and this has created a
situation where you have a small number
of nations that can act with impunity.
These are powerful nations and the rest
of the nations of the world become the
arenas where the powerful nations play
their geopolitical games.
So for example, well um is the 1991 Iraq
war a violation of sovereignty? I
suppose it had it had UN backing
perhaps. What about 2003 the invasion of
Iran Iraq? I suppose that that also had
UN United Nations approval. But what
about the assassination of Kasam Sulmani
in Iraq by the Americans in 2020? That
is clearly a violation of sovereign of
the sovereignty of Iraq. What about the
ongoing war against Iran by the US and
Israel? That is clearly a violation of
Iran's sovereignty. And in response,
Iran has violated the sovereignty of the
whole bunch of nations in the Gulf
region. So when a nation has the might,
it is willing to accept the political
costs
of break of of violating international
law and violating the sovereignty of
other nations. And it is the weaker
nations like the Gulf nations there
which become the arenas where these
geopolitical games are played. That is
the situation. Okay. And one of these
things, one of the violations, one of
the one of the examples of violation of
sovereignty is the assassination of the
supreme leader of Iran. So now the
Americans have created a new normal
where they they all they have to do is
to uh put this tag on nations that this
is a terrorist nation and put a tag on a
person that this leader of the of
whatever nation is a terrorist and that
gives them the justification to kill
people. That's the new normal today. So
by according to you know other nations
could do the same thing tomorrow morning
Mr. Mr. Putin could say that Zelinski is
a terrorist and take him out.
What's preventing Putin from doing the
same thing? Exactly as for the American
rule book. What's preventing Narendra
Modi from tomorrow saying that Aimun is
a terrorist and taking him out? That's
also possible. So if the Americans can
do it, others also could if they can get
away with it do it. So the nations that
are willing to bear the political cost
of violating international law
will do the will do that.
It means that only powerful nations can
do this and the weaker nations
well they pay the price for the the
geopolitical games of the powerful
nations. So where is India today is the
question. So this is not a
civilizational might doctrine. This is a
military might doctrine.
This is an imperial might doctrine. The
nations that are capable of hard
retaliation, they will do these things.
The ones who can't do are not capable of
hard retaliation and are not willing to
to bear the political and other costs of
violating international law, they won't
do it. Right. So other nations are Yeah.
So you're going to have small number of
nations that do these things.
The US is a hard retaliator and hard
it's always played this game of regime
change in and invading other countries.
So the US is one Israel clearly is one
that is willing to go to war. Yeah. It's
willing to initiate wars. US Israel
Russia is a hard retaliator. Eventually
when red lines were crossed it went to
war in Ukraine. So Russia is a hard
retaliator. So you have Iran is a hard
retaliator. They did not initiate the
war, but they have hit back very very
very very hard. So you have the US,
Israel, Russia and Iran that are hard
retaliators and they are willing to bear
the political and material and economic
costs of warfare and of violating
international law.
Is China a hard retaliator? I'm not sure
about China. Thus far, China has stayed
away from these things. China has not
gone to war. It it tries to bully
nations but it has thus far not gone to
war. But time will tell if China also in
the next few months you know takes the
opportunity to make a move on Taiwan.
But China is definitely a very hard
retaliator when it comes to uh economic
retaliation.
So one could say that there are four
five or so nations the US, Israel,
Russia, Iran and maybe China that are
capable of playing these games.
Where does India stand in this right
now? Uh we will time will tell us. Okay.
Real Vadimir Putin says, "What was the
ancient Hindu version of Balojasthan
culture before they converted to to
Islam?" Okay. Where is Balojasthan?
First of all, let's take a look at
Balojasthan.
Where is Balojasthan? So Balojasthan
historically is the border region
between India and Persia. Today
Baljasthan is is split between u Iran,
eastern Iran and the western part of the
temporary uh nation Pakistan. Okay,
that's Balojasthan. So half of roughly
half of Baljasthan is in Iran. Half of
it is in is temporarily in Pakistan. And
historically Balojasthan has been this
uh this this uh you could say transition
zone between India and Persia. So that
is Balojasthan. So you know you have
cities like Guadada and Chabahar that
are in Balojasthan. You you have the
port of Guadada here. This is Guadada.
It's in Balojasthan on the Macran coast.
You also have Chabahar which is in
Balojasthan.
Right. Um
I suppose Iran Shahar is also in
Balojasthan. Chasan and Balojasthan
province.
So that is Baljasthan. Geographically
it's India's western borderlands. Iran's
eastern borderlands. That is
Balojasthan. So what's the history of
Balojasthan? What did Baljasthan look
like before it was Islamized? Right? So
look um if you go back to like let's say
the first millennium BC, second
millennium BC um you know the people of
Balojasthan were the descendants of the
people of the Saraswati Hindu region.
So you know in literature it's called
the harapan
phase of Indian history or the indust
valley phase of Indian history and
Balojasthan is smack bang in the middle
in the western part of this gigantic
region right the saraswati synindu the
sapasindu region so the people of
Balajasan were the descendants of the
the ancient people of this region and
you could say the descendants of the
harapans as we all are actually right
that that sort of thing. So you did not
have any kingdoms that we know of at the
time. Okay. So that is a thing. And then
you had the in the first millennium BC
you have the Aminid dynasty the Persian
the great Persian dynasty of Hakamanish
right the Akirid Empire.
Um and Balojasthan
became kind of part of uh this empire
because this empire it expanded
eastwards all the way to uh the the the
west bank of the Synindhur river the
Indus river. So the the Indis river
became the dividing line between India
and Persia at this time uh especially
during the time of Dios. Das was this
great expansionist king and obviously he
was powerful so he'll expand eastwards
westwards and so he expanded his kingdom
his empire all the way to the west bank
of the indas. So Buljustan came under
the Persian Empire at this time. Then
you have Alexander coming in okay in
whatever 4th century BC right he comes
and he destroys Persia and he wants to
invade India. So he passes through
Balajasthan, enters the Sapasindu
region, is defeated by Porus and then
then limps back to Babylon where he dies
of his injuries or alcoholism or poison
or whatever. So um so Alexander goes
back but he leaves behind uh um
governors and then you have the the the
the what is it called
the Seucid Empire, right? So,
so Balojasthan this region it comes
under Macedonian rule after Persian rule
and then under Seucid rule for a few
years it's under Macedonian rule and
then it's under Seucid rule under the
the as part of the empire of Salucus
Nicator. So Salucas nicer and Chandra
Gupta Moria became allies. They signed a
treaty. Okay. And uh much of the uh
Gandhara etc region was returned to
India but Balojasthan remained under the
Seucid Empire. Okay. Uh after the Seucid
Empire you have various Indo Greek
kingdoms that kind of rule this area you
know Gandhar sind this this region. Um
and some of these were Buddhist some of
these were Hindu.
uh during um the uh Akameid Empire days
in the initial days of the Akameid
Empire uh Balojasthan would have been
Hindu later it would have come under
Zoroastrian rule but it would probably
have remained Hindu the people would
have remained Hindu um so that's the
deal it never essentially was ruled by
the Morian Empire
uh now after the end of the Indo- Greek
era let's say around 100
uh BC or something the first century BC
or something you have Indoparthian rule
in Balojasthan the Paratar Raja Empire
not empire dynasty the Paratar Raja
which is the Parthion Paraja
uh dynasty ruled Balojasthan uh and they
were obviously Hindus you have coins of
the parataraja dynasty with swastikas
all over the place right that sort of
thing so the paratarajas they They ruled
Bulajjasthan for a few centuries and
they are clearly um a clearly a Hindu
kingdom right. Uh and then that kingdom
also eventually declines and then you
have Cassenian Iranian rule over
Baluchasthan.
So the Cadenians were again Zoroastrians
right they they ruled uh
Iran eastern Iran and Baljasthan and
after the Cicadenians you have various
uh you know uh minor Hindu rulers in
Baljasthan and then you have the
invasion of the Arabs from Iran because
by this time by the 7th century or
whatever uh around this time the Arabs
had taken over Persia and from Persia
they made a move onto India through
Baljasthan into Sind And that is the end
of uh yeah the pre-Islamic history of
Buljasthan. I've given a very rough
overview of that. You know I'm sure you
can you can have a whole six-month
course about of the history about the
history of Baljasthan. But overall
that's the kind of the outline of the
history of Balojasthan right the
pre-Islamic history of Baljasthan. If
you go to Baljasthan today you can say
that people are clearly of Indian
origin. They are more Indian than
Persian. Their language is more similar
to uh Cindi and Gujarati than to Persian
clearly right. Their music is very
Indian.
Um and they still have you know some
remnants of Hinduism. For example the
the the the Shakipit of Hind Mata is in
Baluchasthan and people still go there
to worship uh the Dvi right. So there is
still a little bit of uh you know
indigenous culture and religion left in
Baluchasan but mostly today as as as the
case with most of Pakistan most of it is
now uh Islamicized. Okay. So that is the
deal with Baluchistan
real Vladimir Putin says what kind of
democracy did various Mahajanapadas
offer? How was this different from the
modern day version of democracy?
See, I would say that the modern day
version of democracy is the stupidest
form of democracy. Once you are a
certain age, you can vote. No matter
what your IQ is, no matter what your
understanding of the world is, you can
vote.
All you have to do to be able to vote is
to be a certain age.
Yeah. But so that is the modern 20th
century and post 20th century version of
democracy.
But in
older,
more mature or some would say primitive
forms of democracy, everyone wasn't
allowed to vote. For example, let us
examine Greek democracy.
The democracy that you had in Athens and
other Greek city states. Well, according
to the Europeans, Athens and Greece gave
the world democracy. So, let's examine
the form of democracy we had there.
In the Greek city states only wealthy
landowning males could vote.
Okay. So the wealthy landowning males
wealthy landowning population of the
Greek city states was about 10% roughly
of a Greek city state. The rest of them
were either poor people or slaves. Maybe
20 30% of the population were slaves.
The rest were poor people, shepherds and
farmers and whatnot. And about 10% of
the population, male and female, was
wealthy people, landowning people, the
the nobility, the elites.
So out of these 10% only the males could
vote, the the adult males could vote. So
that's about maybe 5% of the population.
These people could vote and these people
could stand for for election.
So it was a very clearly defined small
set of people who could come to power
and who could vote for those who were
standing for power. That was the kind of
democracy you had in Athens and the
Greek city states. Now what kind of
democracy did we have in the
Mahajanapadas the great uh ganarajas
that we had in India
garaj ganasanga that sort of thing. So
you had a large how many 14 or whatever
mahajanapadas you had mala you had baji
you had shakya lchavi uh
kamboja which was in central Asia
essentially right it was northwest of
gandhar. So these were the
Mahajanapadas. Some of these were
actually monarchies but some were
garajas, ganachangas which is republics.
Okay. So in these republics what did you
have? Um you do not have her hereditary
kings. Uh the the authority. Okay. And
power it resided in a ganas sabha jana
sabha or a ganasanga which is a
collective assembly. And that this
assembly had the power to make
decisions, go to war if needed and you
know decide what kind of taxes would you
impose and so on so forth all of that
you know design policies implement
policies so on so forth. So you do not
have hereditary kings you had collective
assemblies. Now what who could become a
member of these assemblies? Was
membership open to everybody or was it
restricted?
So membership was restricted. Okay. Um
it was restricted to
the heads of certain
uh aristocratic chhatria families.
Those who were accustomed to ruling and
who knew how to rule.
Okay. It was so membership was
restricted to the heads of these
families.
um and the rest of the people they would
not uh have any you know any any any any
share of the of the power or governance.
So you these were essentially um you
know you had these elite corporate
bodies that that that
wielded the power and they would elect
their own head who would be a Garaja or
a synapathy or whatever. They could
decide who would be the synapati the
head of the army who would be the
overall ruler gaja or gaka
whatever that sort of thing. So it was
not the democracy in the modern sense of
the of the word that once you are a
certain age no matter who you are you
can vote. It was not like that. Only the
people who were proven to know how to
rule okay they were allowed to to be in
power and uh to vote. Of course at the
lower levels I suppose you would have
anybody could vote for your for your
local uh municipal
body or whatever but when it comes to
the the the apex of power in the Garaja
or Ganesa you know it was not open to
everybody but at the local level to
decide you know who will be your local
municipal head or whatever I suppose
everybody could vote vote for that. Uh
so you had a small inner council or
senate-l like body of of a few uh you
know
powerful people and they would rule and
they would prepare the agendas. They
would decide the the policies. They
would administer the day-to-day affairs.
They would decide about important
matters of of state like warfare about
taxation about this that etc.
educational policies and so on. Right?
Uh so you had collective decision making
right? You had elected uh rulers and
chiefs. You had equal voting among the
assembly members but uh not democracies
in the in the modern sense of the world.
They you could say they were closer in
in nature to the democracy you had in
Greece and Rome. Even in Rome you had
elites who could vote and come to power.
Even in Greece you had elites who could
vote and come to power. And even in
India you had the same thing. So these
systems were very similar. Right?
And you can criticize if it if you want
but it was exactly the same as Greece
and Rome. So um these were aristocratic
democratic republics
uh with with uh deliberative assemb as
assemblies. These were not
the you know these were not like modern
democracy where anybody can vote and
anybody can stand for power. Once again
even in modern democracy technically
anybody can stand for power but you know
your papers are scrutinized the amount
of money you put is criticized and lots
of people are disqualified and even if
you are a allowed to stand for for
election you know you will win election
only if you have if you're able to throw
a tremendous amount of money into the
campaigning process and all of that. So
once again even in India technically
it's free for all
but so but so djour it is it is free for
all technically but in reality only
certain people stand even a small chance
of winning. So technically democracy
seems to be it's open for everybody but
in reality it's not the case. In
reality, you can only stand a chance to
win an election in India if you can
afford to throw, you know, maybe 100 200
crores per election from your pocket or
from the coffers of whatever political
party you may be part of. Only then do
you stand a realistic chance of winning.
So in the old days, none of that BS was
there. You know, none of that hypocrisy
was there. You know what we everybody
can vote and everybody can stand for
power. That's what they claim today. But
we all know that it's not really how it
works. In the old days, it was very
clear. It was very transparent that only
certain
sections of society, the aristocrats
will be allowed to come to power because
they know how to rule. They've been
doing it for for for generations, for
centuries. The other people, well, you
can vote for your local municipal
assemblies and all that, but not for the
top uh top positions. That is what it
was. Exactly the same as Rome, Greece
and so on. But in Rome and Greece you
had slavery. In India you never had
slavery. So that was one dist
distinction between India as opposed to
Rome and Greece. Okay.
Uh real Vladimir Putin says was there
any role of the USSR in the defeat of
the Japanese Empire?
Was there any role of the USSR in the
defeat of the Japanese Empire? So we
talking about the second world war. So
what are the important dates when it
comes to the defeat of the Japanese
Empire?
Um 6th of August 1945
was the first American
nuclear test on Hiroshima.
3 days later 9th of August 1945 was the
second nuclear test on the people of
Nagasaki.
So 6th August, 9th August, what on what
date did Japan surrender? Let's find
out. I think was it was it August 15?
When did Japan surrender in 1945?
Second. Okay. It was announced by
Emperor Hirohito on 15th of August 1945
and formally signed on the 2nd of
September 1945 on a battleship. Right.
So right.
15th of August, it was the Japanese
surrender. 6th August, the first nuclear
test on Hiroshima. 9th August, the
second nuclear test on Nagasaki.
15th of August, surrender.
Now, what was the role of the Soviet
Union in all of this?
So, 6th August, Japan is devastated by a
nuclear test on Hiroshima, right?
in 9th August the second one but one day
before Nagasaki
and 2 days after Hiroshima Hiroshima
which is 8th of August 1945 the USSR
declared war on Japan so the USSR had
this pact of neutrality with Japan
pact of non-aggression or whatever it
was with Japan okay and they walked away
from it unilaterally the Soviets and on
8th August 2 days after the Hiroshi
atomic test the USSR declared war on
Japan. Okay. And it said that it was at
war with Japan and it was joining the
pots dam declaration which called upon
Japan to surrender. So on the 9th of
August early morning the Soviet army the
red army it launched a massive offensive
into Japanese occupied Manuria. This is
called the brief Soviet Japanese war.
Okay. So at that time manuria which is
now part of China which was never
historically part of China. So Manuria
let's find out where is Manuria okay so
that we can orient ourselves.
Manuria
so Manuria
is north of North Korea. Okay, Harbin
you could say is the principal city and
no that's Hilyongjang but this region
overall is Manuria
and you had this region was under
Japanese occupation at the time. Okay,
Manuria.
Uh so 9th August the Soviets invade
Manuria. The Red Army invades Manuria
launches a major offensive and they also
at the same time attacked the Japanese
forces in northern Korea which is
present day North Korea. um the the
Sakalin region, the Kuril Islands.
Once again, let's see the Sakalin region
and Kurill Islands. Okay,
so Sakalin, okay, is this island here.
This island is called Sakalin.
This was well historically you could say
at the time Japanese territory. And the
Kurill Islands are these islands here.
These islands between the Kamchatka
Peninsula over here and Japan.
Historically, these were also Japanese
islands. Even Sakalin at least half of
it was Japanese.
So the USSR then on 9th of August
launched an invasion. Okay. It attacked
um it it launched an offensive in
Japanese occ into into Japanese occupied
Manurya and it also attacked Japanese
forces in northern Korea in uh Sakalin
and the Kurill Islands. And Japan was
already battered. their morale was was
in bad shape because of the atomic test
on Hiroshima and the Soviets very
rapidly uh defeated the Japanese uh
armed forces. They launched a deep uh
armored offensive into Japanese
territory bits [clears throat] style
campaign. Okay. And the Japanese uh uh
resistance collapsed disintegrated
within a few days.
So now what was the set of consequences
this produced for Japan? You see Japan
and the USSR had this uh neutrality pact
or non-aggression pact or whatever.
Okay. And
in August 1945, the Japanese were in bad
shape in the war. Okay. And they
actually were trying to uh
negotiate with the Soviets
and they wanted the Soviets, the Soviet
Union to be their intermediary in their
negotiations with the West so that there
could be some kind of uh uh you know
compromised surrender or compromised
ceasefire, some kind of negotiated
ceasefire with the West. That's what the
Japanese were trying to do. They were
even willing to offer some territory to
the USSR
in exchange for the USSR um facilitating
a negotiated ceasefire with the West
on behalf of Japan.
So, so you see this was their their exit
strategy. This was Japan's diplomatic
exit stat strategy. They wanted to exit
the war and they were hoping the USSR
would help Japan exit the war by
negotiating a ceasefire with the west.
But the USSR, you could say, backstabbed
Japan and entered the war and attacked
Japan, destroyed Japan's last standing
army and destroyed Japan's diplomatic
exit strategy. So the Soviet entry into
the war, it essentially produced
strategic bankruptcy for Japan. Japan
had no good options left.
And then you have Nagasaki.
Yeah. 9th of 9th of August.
So
you could say that the USSR's decision
to suddenly attack Japan,
it you could say it had a consequence
that was even even worse than the atomic
bombings of on Japan. And maybe it was
the USSR's backstabbing that actually
pushed the Japanese leadership
into accepting blanket surrender terms
without any conditions.
Right? So this [laughter]
so the USSR paid played played a major
role
in the way Japan had to surrender.
Yeah. If the USSR had not done this, if
they had played the role of a mediator
between Japan and the West, between
Japan and the United States or the
allies, then maybe Japan could have
possibly agreed to a ceasefire on
certain terms.
But uh yeah, so that's what the USSR did
and that's why Japan, yeah, it it lost
so much territory. It lost the Kural
Islands. That dispute still stands. It
lost Sakalin
and uh it just accepted all the all the
American terms eventually by August 15.
[snorts]
Amisha Mishra says, "Why was Emperor
Hirohito not charged with many with any
war crimes after the Second World War?
And why is Hirohito
never mentioned when discussing the most
dangerous uh evil etc world leaders?"
Right? So 15th of August 1945, Japan
surrenders to the west to to the to the
allies to the Americans and u 2nd
September or whatever they actually
formally sign the surrender uh document
instrument on an American warship. Right
now after the Japanese surrender there
is the Tokyo trial and a large number of
Japanese armed forces personnel, top
armed forces personnel like Hidik tojo
and so on so forth they are put on
trial.
um Hidikito tries to shoot himself in
the chest on in the heart. He does pull
the trigger. He gets shot, but he
somehow survives and eventually he goes
to trial and eventually um he and other
Japanese top ranking military officials
and government officials are hanged for
their alleged war crimes.
So the question is why was Emperor
Hirohito
not charged with war crimes? Why was he
not part of the uh accused in the Tokyo
trials? Right? That's a that's a
question. So
there's political reasons for that. The
Americans
um they wanted to they they had
extracted Japan surrender. They had they
had started they had begun the process
of occupying Japan militarily
and they needed the cooperation of the
people of Japan.
Now, Japanese society
of 1945
was very different from let's say the
Iranian society of 2026.
The Japanese system was very different
from Iran. In Iran,
the Americans today
like two weeks ago assassinated the
supreme leader of Iran.
It made no difference to Iran, right?
Because the Iranian governmental system
and societal stress system is is
decentralized.
The supreme leader is merely an
embodiment
of the legitimacy of the IRGC in Iran.
But the IRGC is not dependent on the
existence of the Supreme Leader. If the
Supreme leader is assassinated, the IRGC
continues to exist and function and they
can put up a new leader any time. You
assassinate that new leader, they'll put
up a third leader. The IRGC is
decentralized. It's like a distributed
system. It's a distributed fault
tolerant system with multiple nodes. You
take out a few nodes, the system still
continues to function.
So the center of gravity Clausovitz Carl
Claus Carl Clausvitz had this uh uh this
this this formalism of the center of
gravity which is the most critical um
you know aspect of a government you take
it out the whole government collapses
right so for Iran it the whole center of
gravity is distributed you kill theata
nothing happens but in Japan 1945
the entire political authority
legitimacy
was embodied in the person of the
emperor. The emperor was the son of god.
You take out the emperor
and the whole system collapses
and society disintegrates. It is no
longer cohesive and killing the emperor
is will be treated by the society as an
unforgivable
crime and they'll rise up in rebellion
and then the Americans will have to
fight Japanese who will be wielding
samurai swords.
They may not have guns but they'll fight
with samurai swords. They'll fight with
knives. So the Americans did not want
that sort of chaos in Japan. They wanted
an orderly takeover of Japan. So they
made the political decision to give
Hirohito, Emperor Hirohito complete
blanket immunity from any prosecution
and they made sure that that the accused
that is the defendants at the Tokyo
trial, they made sure these defendants
did not give any testimony that it that
in any shape or form indicted Emperor
Hirohito in any manner any manner. So
the Americans decided to keep Hirohito
as the puppet figure head of the
government
but the real power will now be in the uh
hands of the Americans but Hirohito will
be the the titular head of government
the emperor Banzai
uh and that's why Hirohito was never
charged with any war crimes to ensure a
stable peaceful orderly takeover of
Japan
and since he was never charged with any
war crimes and all that that's why he
was never mentioned with when discussing
any dangerous world leaders or whatever
and the truth is Hirohito was not not
really the guy in charge ever since the
Maji restoration which was a coup which
was a coup in Japan ever since this
happened the Japanese emperor was just a
figurehead the real people in power were
the people within the government at
lower levels in government below the
emperor they were the people who were
really in power you know bureaucrats and
officials
And the same was the case during the
second world war. Hirohito was merely
the titular emperor. He would sign off
on all decisions. All decisions were
made in the name of Hirohito and he had
to give his ascent or approval. But the
decisions were not taken by him. He
merely gave his approval. So he was not
really as such you know the guy giving
the orders. Of course, at the end of the
day, he was the orders were carried out
in his name with his signature, I
suppose. So, you could say that he was
responsible at the end of the day for
everything, but that's why he was never
charged with war crimes, and that's why
he is not discussed or mentioned when
discussing the MO, the most evil and
murderous and dangerous world leaders.
Okay.
Aayush Singh says, could you please can
you please tell us the history of the
Manipur conflict again? Well, I've done
that multiple times, but I'm sure there
are new viewers who are not aware of the
matter. So, I I can do that once again.
So, uh this what I'm going to tell you
is exactly what I said in in 2023,
right? When the entire disaster
became visible in Manipur,
what is the history of the Banipur
conflict? There are so many manipur
experts these days, right?
um who have their own versions of what
hap what's happening who the heroes are
and who the villains are and so on but
what's the real history of the Manipur
conflict to understand the real history
of Manipur of the Manipur conflict you
have to understand the history of
Manipur itself what is Manipur
so Manipur is this present day state in
the far east of India let's take a look
at it right where is this let's go to
the map and quickly take a look at it
and orient ourselves which part of India
are we referring to so this India as we
know. Zoom in. Go to the east of India.
The far east of India. And here you have
Manipur. This is Manipur. The capital
city isal. East of Manipur. You have
Burma.
Burma. Now called Myanmar. Right? So
today Manipur is one of the states of
India. Historically it was a kingdom. It
historically it was much larger over at
various points in time. There was a time
when the king of Manipur captured
Manderlay. Manderlay over here. Right.
uh there was a time when the king of
Manipur even conquered parts of Yunan in
China and there were times when Manipur
was under Burmese occupation and so on.
So that is Manipur. Now let's understand
Manipur a little bit better. We know
there's something called the Manipuri
language, right? We know that Manipur I
mean some of you may know that Manipur
has a written record of kings going back
at least 2,000 years.
Um so you could say three and a half
thousand years. So you have a written
record of each king of Manipur over the
past three and a half thousand years the
Ningtoja dynasty and you have the
Manipuri language and you some of you
may also know that Manipur is the state
that has given India one of its
so-called classical dances the Manipuri
classical dance and nutsan and so on
these you know these different
manifestations of Manipuri culture
that's what Manipuri is famous for so
you ask yourself the question now today
if you look at Manipur the demographics
of Manipur There are three main
population groups today in Manipur. One
is the matees, one is the Nagas and one
is the cookies. The question today is
and lots of people are confused about
this. The question is who are the
original inhabitants of Manipur? H
that's the question. Is it the cookies?
Is it the Nagas? Is it the matees? Who
are the true inhabitants, original
indigenous people of Manipur? You to
understand that to understand the
conflict.
So you have a wellestablished
historical record of the kings of
Manipur dating back to at least 2,000
years before today.
A large number of kings.
The question is which ethnic group did
all these kings belong to? Were they
Naga? Were they cookie? Or were they
matei? The answer is that every single
king of Manipur was mate over the past
2,000 years. Matei, not Naga. Some of
them had Naga blood also but there's no
cookie. Number two, the Manipuri
language. Which ethnic group speaks the
Manipuri language? That has been around
for at least 2,000 years. Is it the
cookies? Is it the mates? Is it the
Nagas? It is the Mateis who speak the
Manipuri language that has been in
existence for at least 2,000 years.
Manipuri classical dance. Manipuri not
the Sankran.
Which ethnic group gave this? Which
ethnic group is the progeniator of these
cultural manifestations? Is it the
Mateies? Is it the Nagas? Is it the
cookies? It's the Matees. So, Manipuri
language is a mate language. Every
Manipuri king was a mate king. Manipuri
dance is a mate art form. Manipuri
Natkan is mate.
Okay.
So, Manipur, the history of Manipur is
essentially the history of the Mateis.
And the Nagas, the people who are called
the Nagas, they are various tribes.
They are all
ethnically and genetically related to
the Matees. But they live in the hills
today. And the Matees, they live in the
small portion of Manipur, whether it's
the Infal Valley. So the Matees and the
Nagas, [snorts] they have blood
relations going back at least 2,000
years. And they are the indigenous
people of Manipur.
Okay,
that is established now and you can fact
check that. You can fact check that.
What am I what whatever I'm saying
[clears throat] now the cookies where
did they come from is the question. So
if you see u so Manipur has this 2000
year history of kings it has its own
language it has its own system of
writing its own script. So Manipur is
like a mini civilization in its own
right and it's historically its religion
was a polytheistic religion. In English
it is called sanamism polytheistic
religion and eventually it synretized
with what we call Hinduism. And today a
large number of mates practice
Vishnovism and some practice a
combination of Vishnavism and what is
calledism and some are only practice
only.
uh the the Nagas were all Christianized
by the efforts of Shri Huji in the 20th
century. Now if you look at British
census records
okay now before the British census
records Manipur was independent as a
kingdom for 2,000 years. Then in 1800
early 1800s Manipur came under British
under Burmese occupation 7 years of
devastation. Okay. And after the Burmese
were evicted from Manipur,
this happened. At this time the Brit
British became relevant and they started
taking over power in Manipur.
To make a long story short, in 1891, the
Manipuris went to war against the
British to eject them from Manipur and
the British were able to defeat the
Manipuris and that's when Manipur loses
its sovereignty and the British install
a fake puppet king
and that's how they they they defeat
they destroy the sovereignty of Manipur
and the Mateis fought a war against the
British. So to punish the matees the
British
they enacted a policy to forcibly
confine the mate people to about 6% of
the population of of the territory of
manipur that is the infal valley the
manipur the mates were prevented from
having any property outside little Ial
valley and to punish the mis further the
British started settling
foreign tribals in Manipur from Burma
and these are the cookies so if you Look
at the census records of Manipur,
British census records from 1900 and so
on in 1900 around that time you will see
less than maybe 1% of the population of
Manipur was cookies and those two were
brought in by the British as foreigners
who were settled in Manipur to punish
the mates.
And then over the next few decades the
British brought in more and more cookies
in Manipur and these are all
Christianized. Then after 1949 when
Manipur officially became a part of
India, the government of India for
whatever reason continued settling
cookies into Manipur.
Now if you look at the satellite images
of Manipur over the past 10 years, over
the past 10 years you will see thousands
of new villages coming up in Manipur.
That is lacks of cookies crossing over
from Burma into Manipuri territory and
taking over more than half of Manipur.
That is the Manipur conflict. The
Manipur conflict is
what is the root cause? It is the
foreign occupation of more than half of
Manipur by foreigners, foreign
infiltrators. Just like Bangladesh is,
just like Rohi's cookies have come in,
the borders are open. They've just
walked in and taken over territory and
they are terrorizing the locals.
And you have American and Ukrainian
mercenaries who are coming in crossing
over from Misoram into Burma coming with
drones imparting terrorism training to
the cookies giving them drones and
whatnot. And the drones since 2023 have
been used to target Manipuri civilians
and kill them.
So um the cookies they have weapons all
kinds of weapons unlimited supply of
weapons arms ammunition and so on. So
this is the Manipur conflict. The
Manipur conflict. What is the root
cause? The presence of lacks of
foreigners in Manipur.
Okay. Who are the victims? The
indigenous people of Manipur are the
victims. The mates and the Nagas.
That is the history of the Manipur
conflict. And this is a story. This is
not a story. This is the history I have
been saying since 2023. It has not
changed. Okay. And uh today the things I
have been saying since 2023 they they
are now coming out they are now being
proven to be true slowly slowly the
truth is coming out isn't it right just
a few days ago this American terrorist
was was arrested along with six
Ukrainian mercenaries
right
um last year the chief minister of
misoram he said that more than around
2,000 foreigners had come to money to to
Misoram over the past year or so
you US and UK nationals who were not
really tourists.
So this is a geopolitical game to to
destabilize the region and to create a
de facto artificial nation called cookie
land cookie land for Christ
to to create more chaos for India and
more trouble for India. So that
essentially is the Manipur conflict.
Okay.
Amisha Mishra says, "Tensions between
Afghanistan and Pakistan have reportedly
escalated after claims that drone
strikes were carried out on targets
across the border. What triggered the
latest escalation? Details of the
reported drone strike claims historical
context of Afghanistan Pakistan tensions
possible regional and geopolitical
impact # geopolitics. Well, this is a
historical question as much as a
geopolitical question. And just like the
Manipur conflict, let's understand the
Afghanistan Pakistan conflict. What is
the context? Why does it exist? So why
are Pakistan and Afghanistan hostile to
each other? Aren't they both Sunni
Islamic nations, Sunni Muslim nations as
Muslim nations should not be they be
friendly, brotherly ties? Should should
they not have? So why do these two
nations hate each other? What is the
root cause of the conflict? And it's a
intractable conflict. It's not going
anywhere. What is the cause of the
conflict is the question. The root cause
of the Afghanistan Pakistan conflict is
a massive border dispute.
See
Afghanistan is Gandhar. Gandhar is the
first part of India uh that was
Islamized as a consequence of the Turic
introgression into India, the Turk
invasions of India. [snorts] So the
first part of India, Daratwash that was
that was conquered by the Turks and
Islamized was Gandhar, Afghanistan and
then slowly over centuries they they
came slowly further into India and
eventually they took over large parts of
India. So Afghanistan is the original
Kashmir. Okay.
And [snorts]
much of Afghanistan was Islamized. uh
until the 20th late 20th century you
still had a few lakh maybe about a lack
of Hindus and and and six in Afghanistan
but today there's almost no Hindu no
almost maybe a handful of Hindus and six
left in Afghanistan most of them have
escaped to India so those Afghan Hindus
and six who escaped to India they were
pons
okay ethnically they were pons but by
religion they were Hindus and sik and
the pashons are anyway an extension of
the northern Indian ethnicity countries
uh they are extension of the northern
Indian population. Now Afghanistan
because it was Islamized for a thousand
years. It waged war against the southern
parts of India for centuries. Uh the
Gores started that then the Gnavis
started the continued that and so on.
Then you had the Abdales and so on. So
there was a time when the Afghans they
had conquered
and occupied Kashmir and they were very
cruel to the people of Kashmir and they
did all kinds of atrocities and
brutalities and so on. um you know and
then what happens is in the 19th century
um [snorts]
Maharajit Singh establishes the stick
empire and is a very vigorous
um conqueror and he liberates Kashmir
from the Afghans
and uh to punish the Afghans for the
atrocities they did on Kashmir he takes
some Afghan territory as well and makes
it part of the Sik Empire.
Okay. and uh he reestablishes dharma in
Kashmir. He again bans cows slaughter
and so on and so forth. Okay. So that is
Baharaja and Jjit Singh. This is what he
did. So to punish the Afghans for their
atrocities on the Kashmiris, he took a
large part of Pashon territory as well
and made it part of the Sikh Empire. Now
after Maharaja Ranjit Singh's demise
very rapidly his empire collapsed. It
was taken over by the British by the
British and whatever territories
Maharaja Ranjit Singh had conquered the
British made those territories part of
British India including the Pashun part
of the Sikh Empire that Ranjit had
conquered from the Afghans.
After 1947
that Pashon part of British India became
part of Pakistan.
But if you go there, it is pun
dominated. The people there are puns
mostly. Today it's called Kar Pakuna.
And the line that divides Pakistan from
Afghanistan is called the Durand line.
And the Afghans say that this is an
imaginary line that we don't recognize
and don't respect. And the Afghans say
that Kyber Pakuna is Pashon territory.
It should be back. It should be part of
Afghanistan. It should not be part of
Pakistan. We will never recognize it as
part of Pakistan. And that is the major
border dispute. As long as Khibar
Pakunwa is part of Pakistan, there will
never be peace between Afghanistan and
Pakistan.
And on top of that, you have the
Pakistanis who perpetrate barbaric
atrocities in the people of Afghanistan.
They've launched drone strikes. They've
launched air strikes on Kabul. A recent
air strike hit a hospital that was a
rehabilitation center for drug addicts.
and about 3 400 patients
unarmed civilians were killed by the
Pakistanis. Right? So that's the deal.
So the Afghans will the Taliban
government will will never allow the
Pakistanis to get away with this. So the
Afghans may not have a fully
professional, well-trained, well
equipped army. They may not have nuclear
weapons, but they know how to fight
guerrilla warfare and they're going to
make life miserable for the Pakistanis.
Right? So that is the deal. That's the
deal.
And Afghanistan and India historically
well have had good relations right. I
mean one of the tallest leaders of who
was a pashon was Khan Abdul Kafar Khan
and Khan Abdul Kafar Khan spent his
whole life fighting for a united India
united independent India. He opposed the
creation the formation of Pakistan
and when Pakistan was formed Khan Abdul
Galar Khan told Mr. Gandhi that you have
thrown us to the wolves
and Khan Abdul Kafar Khan spent much of
the rest of his life under house arrest.
Okay. Khan Abdulbar Khan wanted a
unified united India.
So he was pashon he was the pashon
leader and uh when he died I think he
was buried in Afghanistan in I don't
know Jalabad or whatever right. So yeah,
so Afghanistan, India, we have we have
always had good relations in the past
century or so. And uh
I I I wish our Afghan brothers and
sisters success against this barbaric,
evil, terrorist nation, temporary nation
of Pakistan. Hopefully we solve this
problem soon.
Real Vader Putin says how did Hindu
kings deal with differences that existed
in Indian society? We had thousands of
jatis and hundreds of languages.
So imagine you are in a corporation. You
are you are you are u uh an employee in
a corporation. Let's say you are in an
IT firm. Let's say you are a programmer.
But let's say you have colleagues who
are testers who do QR QA testing,
quality assurance testing.
So your jati is programmer, their jati
is QA tester. You're totally different
people, right? And then you have
technical writers, that is a third jati.
Then you have the uh HR people, that's a
fourth jati. Then you have the
managerial staff, that's a fifth jati.
Then you have the canteen people who who
ensure that everybody is wellfed. No,
that's a sixth jati.
So even in a corporation you have so
many jatis
are these differences
do do these differences make you hate
each other? Not quite right. You all
work together. If any of these jatis is
removed from the corporation
the entire functioning of the
corporation collapses in a certain way.
Some are more important, some are less
important, but all are important and all
perform a certain role in this cohesive
environment that is the corporation.
Now, Indian society historically to
extend the analogy, Indian society had
thousands, tens of thousands of jatis.
These were occupation based jatis. Some
were jewelers, some were goldmiths, some
were iron smith, iron smiths, some were
textile, some made textiles. Uh, some
were warriors, some were teachers, some
were gurus, uh, some were god knows
what, sailors,
some some you had so many different
professions and occupations. India was
the world's full first fully
industrialized civilization.
Some were architects, some were masons,
some were stone workers, some were
concrete workers, some made bridges,
some made roads. These were all
different jatis.
These are entire lineages that
specialized in one specific profession.
Super specializations.
These were not differences. This this
was harmony.
All these different jatis they provided
very specific services to society and
they were all integral parts of society.
These are not differences. This is
called organization of society. It's
called division of labor. We all need
all these things to be done but we will
all specialize in different things and
we will all work cohesively and
harmoniously to have this highly evolved
and well functioning society. But today
that is portrayed by our historians and
our professors and academics as
differences.
So if if you go to university
and you have one professor who's from
the physics department, one from the
maths department, one from sociology,
one from whatever chemistry,
are these differences or are they just
colleagues who are all providing
different services to the students and
eventually these services are provided
to society. Are these differences or are
they actually colleagues who are working
together in different roles but the same
function and they're all serving
society.
So today we are made to see things in a
in in a way that makes us imagine that
everything is a further division of
society and everybody is hostile to each
other. Nobody was hostile to each other.
But today in today's India politics is
such that this this this cast politics
has made everybody hostile to each
other.
That's the problem. And we see
everything from from the prism of
today's world.
But ancient India was not like that.
Ancient India was a harmonious society.
Right? Of course some people earned
more, some some people earned less and
so on so forth. Every society has these
these you know um these issues. These
are not issues. These are these are uh
these are features of society. Not
everybody will earn the same.
Right? You go to any corporation does
everybody earn the same? No. The manager
earns more.
A programmer junior programmer earns
less and so on. That's how it is.
So there was no need to deal with
imagined differences. There were no
differences. Kings, they had one simple
role to ensure that society prospers and
society remains safe. And that's what
they focused on. They did not have to
focus on differences in society. There
was no difference in society.
Okay. All right. Next.
Brown Leprechaun says, "How effective
are the This is a This is from three
weeks ago. How effective are the THAD
and Patriot missile system? Also,
when was the last time the US won
a war singlehandedly?
When was the last time the US won a war
single-handedly against anybody against
anybody?
Okay, so let me deal with the THA and
Patriot system. So, THAAD is terminal
high altitude area defense. Okay. Um,
the THAAD system has this massively
expensive radar. One radar costs more
than a billion dollars. And they have
this very expensive missiles. One
missile like between one to one to three
1 to5 million per piece. And uh you will
need multiple missiles to take out an
incoming threat. Typically a ballistic
missile. So that's a THAD system. And uh
how effective is it? Well, it's only as
effective as the radar. And if you
destroy the radar, the THAD system is
blind. And the Iranians have been taking
out the THAD radars. The THAD system is
not working anymore. So that's how
effective it is. It may be very
effective. It may be very accurate. But
you kill the radar, the whole system is
blind, right? The Patriot system, once
again, very expensive system and not
very accurate. You need multiple Patriot
interceptor missiles to take take out an
incoming ballistic missile. Obviously,
it's it's like shooting a bullet with a
bullet. It's very difficult. And uh
yeah, it's it's the Iran war has shown
that the Patriot and AD systems are
extremely economically ineffective
because uh each interceptor missile
costs millions of dollars while the
incoming ballistics and drones cost a
fraction of that. Quantity has a quality
of its own. I've been saying for how
many years? Well, you're seeing it in
action in front of your eyes now.
Quality quantity has a quality of its
own.
This is the lesson India really
desperately urgently needs to learn. Now
the the more pertinent historical
question since we are dealing with
history today.
When was the last time the United States
won a war singleendedly?
Good question. So let's think about some
of the wars the United States has uh
fought in the reasonably recent past.
There's an ongoing war the Americans are
fighting. It's against Iran, but they're
not fighting alone. Israel is fighting
alongside the US. And the various Gulf
nations are also kind of providing some
services to the US. So the US is not
fighting single-handedly. It's not
fighting alone against Iran. Iran is
fighting a eight or nine front war. In
India, we worry about a two and a half
front war, right? Iran is fighting an
eight or nine front war. So this is not
war. The US is fighting single-handedly.
2003, the Iran Iraq invasion, sorry,
Iraq invasion. This was the US and a
coalition of other nations that
collectively invaded Iraq and deposed
Saddam Hussein. So it was not
single-handed victory. 1991 Iraq once
again once again a coalition of nations
attacked Iraq. So it was not a
single-handed victory. Before that you
had uh Vietnam. The Americans lost
Vietnam. So that was a loss. There was a
defeat for the US. Before that you had
the Korean War which was not a victory
for the US. they lost half of the Korean
peninsula. So you could say it was kind
of semi-defeat for the US and once again
the US was not fighting alone. So u uh
it was a a semi-defeat for the US. The
second world war the Americans you can
say won but they were one of the allies
and they had a whole bunch of nations
that was fighting against the Nazis and
the Soviets and the Italians and much of
the fighting
and dying and winning was done by the
USSR not by the US. So the US did not
win this war single-handedly and before
that. So which is the last war the
Americans won single-handedly. You had
the US Mexico war in the 1800s that they
won. But uh after that there was one
more war I can think of that the
Americans won single-handedly.
That was the um
Spanishamean war. Spanishame war of
1898.
Okay. So that is a war in which the
Americans defeated Spain
single-handedly. 1898 you have to go all
the way back. So the Americans um
defeated Spain. They uh liberated Cuba
from Spanish Spanish occupation. They
also liberated uh Philippines and Guam
from Spanish occupation. But the
consequence was that the Americans
occupied the Philippines. They they
essentially bought the Philippines from
Spain for about 10 million or something
dollars, 1020 million. And then the
Filipinos went to war against the
Americans because they wanted to be
free. But the Americans, they
effectively replaced Spanish occupation
of the Philippines with American
occupation of the Philippines.
So there was no difference for the for
the Filipinos, right? Uh so anyway, that
led to the US Philippines war, which the
Americans eventually won, but the that
was not a major war. It's hardly a war.
So the last war the Americans won was
the uh 1898 Spanish American War. Since
then, they have never won a war
single-handedly.
is truth. Yes. Is very much truth.
Okay.
Um Swami says, "Shouldn't Rome and
Byzantine Empire be considered to be
different
as Rome was pagan and the Byzantine
Empire was Christian? Also, why do you
say that the capital of the British
Empire shifted from London to
Washington? Aren't they separate
entities too?" Good question. that a
good question that allows me to explain
this in a little more detail. So Rome,
the Roman Empire and the Byzantine
Empire, shouldn't they be considered
different? The Roman Empire was pagan.
The Byzantine Empire was Christian. So
should they not be considered to be
different? Well, you see, Christianity
became a thing in the Byzantine Empire
in the 4th century AD.
before the 4th century AD around the
time the Byzantine Empire was still
pagan and secondly the origin of the
Byzantine Empire is Rome itself.
So it depends on what sort of lens you
want to use for your analysis. If you
want to look at the situation in 1,00 AD
then clearly the Byzantine Empire is a
completely separate Christian empire and
there is no Western Roman Empire in
existence around 10,000 AD. Even 500 AD
the Byzantine Empire is a major eastern
Christian empire and the Roman Empire is
mostly disintegrated in the west. So
again two completely separate entities.
But if you go back to 200 AD then the
Byzantine Empire
is nothing but an offshoot of the
Western Roman Empire.
So understand that the origin of the
Byzantine Empire is as a child of Rome
and eventually it it it took took its
own life its own separate existence
eventually.
So eventually they were different. Today
India and Pakistan are different.
But that that that is relevant. If you
look at 2026, if you look at 1945, there
was no Pakistan. Do you understand this
simple difference?
So eventually the Byzantine Empire
became a distinct separate entity from
the Roman Empire and it significantly
out outlasted the Roman the Western
Roman Empire. But the Byzantine Empire,
there was a time when there was no
Byzantine Empire and there was only a
Roman Empire and then the Roman Empire
gave birth to a child in Byzantium which
became Constantinople and eventually
became a separate entity. Do you
understand the difference
and eventually even when it was born the
Byzantine Empire was originally pagan
just like Rome polytheistic and later it
became Christian. Please understand the
chronology, understand how things
evolve.
And the same can be said about the
British Empire and the American Empire.
It's the Anglo-Saxon Empire.
Okay? It's the capital of the
Anglo-Saxon Empire that moved from
London, UK to Washington
DC. Okay? It's the Anglo-Saxon Empire
which encompasses much of the world.
Australia, Canada, the UK, New Zealand
and the US are part of the Anglo-Saxon
Empire and all their vasal states and
occupied states like Japan, Germany,
South Korea, etc. These and EU EU NATO
nations these are all part of the
Anglo-Saxon Empire. Some are vasal
states, some are allied states, some are
states under occupation and some are
actually Anglo-Saxon states. Understand
that?
So that's what happened.
Okay.
So,
originally you had a British Empire and
the United States was this
relatively weaker entity,
but it was the same people, the same
culture. Eventually, the US became the
lifeline for the UK in the Second World
War. And that's when the center of
gravity moves from London to Washington.
Right. Okay.
Swami once again says how important
is the Siber Siberia region Russia if
hypothetically Russia loses it would
Russia just become a boxedin state in
Europe like Poland Hungary etc that is
super easy to invade excellent excellent
interesting question uh first of all
let's look at Siberia
uh let's put the map on the screen Okay.
So, Russia is the world's largest nation
um and broadest widest nation from east
to west or west to east. Yes. I don't
know 11 12 or whatever time zones 15
time zones whatever it is whatever the
actual number is. And which part of
Russia is Siberia? Well, I suppose it's
the uh from where does it begin? I
suppose
um
yakutsk
and all the way to um yeah this overall
region Eurasian region uh does Google
let's see Siberia
does it give us a separate okay so this
uh shaded region is Siberia I would not
really include sakalin and vladi was
part of Siberia but Okay, technically it
seems to be part of that even Kamchatka.
So this is Siberia. It's eastern Russia.
It's you could say Asiatic Russia that
is u Siberia and then you have European
Russia which is uh uh essentially west
of the Ural mountains and that's the uh
European or Eastern European portion of
of Russia. But the largest portion is
the Asia is the Eurasian or Asiatic part
of Russia which is Siberia. Right? So
the question you're asking is how
important is Siberia for Russia? It is
super important. It's critically
important. It's vitally important.
Most of um the resources that Russia has
are in Siberia. Whether it is metal ore,
whether it's iron ore, whether it is
diamonds, whether it is uh various
chemicals, whether it is oil, whether
it's gas, oil, gas must be caucases
region. But much so much more. um the
agricultural land, the the strategic
depth Russia has um the the ability for
Russia to have an eastern seabboard on
the Pacific coast,
um the proximity to so many nations in
Indonesia. All of that is thanks to
Russia uh owning Siberia. It's thanks to
Siberia being part of Russia. Whenever
Russia has gone to war and it's been
under stress like for example during the
second world war you had operation
Barbarosa and the so the Nazis occed
Russia they came all the way to the
outskirts of Moscow how did Russia
survive that they moved all their
production lines all their factories
into the interiors of Russia which is
into Siberia they could just keep going
east even if they're invaded right and
that's why Russia was able to survive
um so this gigantic piece of uh uration
territory gives Russia tremendous
strategic depth. It gives Russia this
inexhaustible re, you know, reservoir of
resources. It's what makes Russia an
otarchy, right? So, it's it's critically
important for Russia, the Siberia
region, right? If hypothetically Russia
loses Siberia, will Russia become a
boxed in state in Europe just like
Poland, Hungary, etc. Super easy to
invade? Uh, not quite. So, once again,
let's go to the map. Yeah,
if you see the non-Siberian part of
Russia, yeah, it is still way larger
than Poland or Hungary. Way larger.
Huge. Huge compared to Poland or
Hungary. Much larger than Ukraine, it is
still the largest entity in uh in in the
whole of Europe. Even if it loses
Siberia, so it will not become a boxedin
state like Poland or Hungary. Poland is
not quite boxed in. It has a sea
seabboard sea coast. Hungary is a
landlocked country. If Russia loses
Siberia, it will still have access uh to
the Black Sea and the Caspian Sea and
also the the Bar Sea, right? So, it
won't be entirely landlocked at all. Uh
but it will lose obviously its its
precious resources in Siberia and it
won't be that easy to invade. It will be
relatively easier to invade but still
it'll still be a formidable uh opponent
to have.
Okay.
Nirvana Shanks says, "During the
Anglo-Saxon period before 1066 AD, how
much cultural and political influence
did the Saxon elite retain in the
English court? And to what extent did
the English bureaucracy retain
Anglo-Saxon structures after the Norman
conquest of 1066 AD and where were they
were they replaced by Norman systems?"
interesting question but I cannot go
into such tremendous details because
even I don't remember exactly what
specific structures and bureaucratic
structures and all we had in in England
but let me give you a higher level
overview okay so before 1066 AD
England was ruled by the Anglo-Saxons
the Angles and Saxons invaded England
sometime in the fifth century roughly AD
Okay. They invaded from present day
Germany. Saxony and so on. Anglia. Yeah.
Angles, Saxons and Judes came from
Germany and England and invaded England.
So before the Anglo-Saxon and Jude
invasions in the fifth century,
England was ruled by Celtic peoples.
[snorts]
Of course, England was under uh Romanal
occupation for a few centuries and
before the Romans, you had the Celtic
peoples who uh and Britonic peoples uh
who ruled England. So, if you look at
England's population in the 11th century
AD before 1066 AD, you had a mix of
Anglo-Saxons
and Celtic peoples who were part of the
English population. Okay? And in 1066 AD
you have the Norman invasion of England
by William of Normandy day who was then
called William the Bastard. But after
1066 AD he was known as William the
Conqueror.
Now
in the 11th century AD uh the Saxon
elite retained all the influent
influence in the English court. All of
it not how much all of it.
So England had cultural elements that
came from the Celtic people, right? From
the um from the northern from the north
northern lands, you know, Scotland,
Ireland, all that. And England had lots
of cultural elements that came in from
uh the Scandinavian peoples
for for a few for a few centuries. uh
the English paid the Dana gel to the to
the to the to the Vikings, yearly
tribute of gold to the Vikings for a for
a various period of periods of time.
England was ruled by Scandinavian kings.
For example, Canute the Great in the
11th century AD,
probably 11th century AD. And then he
and Kenut the Great had this great
friend who was an earl of his whose name
was Earl Godwin. He was uh Anglo-Saxon.
He was a Saxon lord and he was a good
friend of King Kanut and he had fought
with King Kut in Scandinavia in various
wars and they were good friends. So Earl
Godwin was the first among the the
nobility of England. Um so King Kenut
was Scandinavian and Earl Godwin was
Anglo-Saxon. So King Kenut dies and he
leaves behind three or four sons. One of
them is the king of England and you have
two sons in Scandinavia. One is Harold
Herford was it? The one is Swain and so
on. Messed up thing. Yeah. And Earl
Godwin has a number of sons. One is
Swain. He was an absolute crackpot.
Nutcase. The oldest son Swain. His
second son was was it Harold. Third was
Tostig
and so on. Wolf not also somewhere.
So you had the Anglo-Saxon
people who were the elite, the nobility
and they had a very welldefined very
well organized system of governance of
of uh the British islands. Okay. And
then you have um so so eventually Harold
the son of Earl Godwin became the king
of England. He was appointed the king.
Uh before him you had Edward the
Confessor, wasn't it? Edward the
confessor who who was a peculiar person.
He is uh regarded as a saint today. He
married
the daughter of Earl Godwin
but they apparently never uh had normal
marital relations, never had children.
Um and uh
yeah, Edward the Confessor,
his mother was Norman, but he hated his
mother because she did not ever love him
or something, some messed up story and
so on. And eventually after he dies, you
have uh u Harold Godwinson who the son
of Earl Godwin who becomes the king of
England
in the year 1066. That's when all hell
breaks loose. Harold Hardrada invades
England from the north with King
Harold's brother Tostig and King Harold
kills them both in a massive massive
devastating battle battle of Stamford
Bridge and the moment he wins the battle
of Stamford Bridge news comes to him
that Duke William of Normandy has
invaded England in the south. So he has
to run with his battered and beaten army
all the way down south and he has to
meet the Norman invaders at Hastings and
uh yeah Harold got unlucky. He got a you
know arrow in his eye and that was the
beginning of Norman rule. Now once the
normals Normans Normans started ruling
England they continued much of the same
system of governance that the
Anglo-Saxons had established. was a very
good system of governance.
You had shiers, you had hundreds and so
on. And then the Normans under William
of Normandy, they did what? The great
survey of England. They compiled the
Doomsday book.
Okay? And if you study the Doomsday
book, you'll find that at least 10% of
England's population was slaves at the
time and so on. So that's how it
happened overall. uh the details of the
bureaucracy and structures and all you
can read them in your own free time but
overall this is how it happened. Very
interesting period of time in the
history of England.
Abishek says please share your views on
the belief that Mongols worshiped Lord
Shiva. Well that belief is entirely
incorrect.
There is no evidence whatsoever that the
Mongols worshiped Lord Shiva.
Okay.
And I'm talking about the time
up to the 13th century AD. The until
Shir Chingis Khan was still alive.
So the original religion of the Mongol
people and the Turk people also is
called in English language it's called
Tangism. And a lot of people try to
portray this as a monotheistic religion.
The worship of the one true god Tangri
which is BS.
In the Mongolian religion, there is the
worship of the sky father Tangri, the
earth mother Umay, which is like dio and
prituimata in our
old Vic religion, right? You also have
the the worship of ancestors, the
spirits of your ancestors, the spirits
of the forest, you worship trees, you
worship hills, you worship mountains.
So, it's a polytheistic religion. Okay.
And eventually u after the uh Mongol
conquest of China
um Shri Kubla Khan made uh Buddhism
Tibet and Vajriana Buddhism the de facto
state religion of the Mongols. But the
Mongols already practiced what is called
Tangism in English. So Tangism and
Vajriana Buddhism synretatized.
And today if you go to Mongolia you have
Mongol Mongolian people who will have in
their house a portrait of Shri Chingish
Khan. They will have a portrait of the
Buddha and they will also have uh
tenrist uh worship elements in their
house right that's how it is. They will
have swastikas in the necklaces and the
musical instruments and knives and
whatnot. So it's a very syncritic
culture that you have in Mongolia today
religion and in vajana Buddhism Tibetan
Buddhism there is
the existence of Maheshwara Lord Shiva
but typically in Vajayana Buddhism
Maheshwara or Lord Shiva is depicted as
being trampled under the feet of tantric
deities.
Okay is true?
Fact check me. Go on. So that's the
deal. Okay. The Mong the Mongols do have
the trishul in Tangism but that's a
Tristul. It's not a it's not the trishul
of Lord Shiva. It's a polytheistic
culture and a lot of things come up you
know emerge spontaneously that are very
similar across neighboring cultures. So
the Mongols did not worship Lord Shiva
at least until the time of Shir
Chinghan. Later on because of Indian
influences which came in through Tibet.
Maybe some people may have perhaps
worshiped Lord Shiva perhaps but those
would be a big significant minority.
Today you have a syncratic version
syncratic form of vajayana Buddhism and
Tangorism that is practiced in Mongolia
just like in Japan you have a syncratic
syncretic synretic version of Shinto and
Buddhism and Hinduism practiced in in
Japan. that sort of thing.
Okay. Um I have more questions but I
think I should end it now because it's
like over two hours. I typically these
days do four and a half hour live
streams but let's end this one at a
reasonable time. Taking a whole bunch of
questions. So um yeah.
Yes. Okay. So I will end the live stream
here um at a reasonable time today for a
change. Uh today the super chat is off
because I wanted to end the stream after
two 2 and a half hours like I'm doing
now. Tomorrow I'm going to have a live
stream in which the super chats will be
on and we can take it 4 hours 4 and a
half hours how as as long as you want. I
will take all of a super chats. Yes, you
are right. Whoever it is here the Garuda
is the national bird of Mongolia. Yes,
that is true. And the Garuda comes into
Mongolia through Tibetan culture. Right.
Right. Okay. So, I look forward to
seeing you all tomorrow. Tomorrow we're
going to discuss everything including
the Iran war, geopolitics, all that back
to normal programming. But I thought
I'll do a history session today just to,
you know, calm the temperature to cool
the temperature down a little bit. All
right. So, I look forward to seeing you
tomorrow in less than 24 hours. Take
care. Keep asking questions. Keep
learning. Keep raising your standards.
And I will see you in tomorrow's live
stream. Thank you everybody. Good day.
Good day. Good night. Bye-bye for now.